Guide to the Pioneer America Society records, 1964-1980
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Pioneer America Society records
1964-1980
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives
Henry H. Douglas
7 linear feet (13 boxes)
The Pioneer America Society Collection (PAS) contains material related to the activities of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the PAS from 1967 to 1980. Additionally, the collection includes the publications and findings of the Chapter during that time period, including photographs and maps. The collection is divided into five series for easy use and research.
C0011
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by the Estate of Henry H. Douglas (David F. MacGhee, Executor) in 1989.
Historical Information
The Pioneer America Society (PAS) is a national non-profit organization dedicated to the preservation and study of sites that represent North American history and material culture. Organized in 1967 by Henry H. Douglas, a resident of Falls Church, Virginia, the Society documents and interprets architecture and artifacts in addition to encouraging education, research, and preservation.
Scope and Content
The Pioneer America Society Collection (PAS) contains material related to the activities of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the PAS from 1967 to 1980. Additionally, the collection includes the publications and findings of the Chapter during that time period, including photographs and maps. The collection is divided into five series for easy use and research. The five series are: Northern Virginia Chapter Business from 1969 to 1979, Correspondence from 1967 to 1978, arranged alphabetically, Subject Files from 1967 to 1978, Printed Material from 1964 to 1980, and Oversize materials from the 1970s.
The first series, Northern Virginia Chapter Business, covers the period from 1969 to 1979. This series is composed of materials pertaining to the activities of the Northern Virginia Chapter and includes the Chapter history, membership, interest sheets, and newspaper clippings. Also included in this series are the Chapter minutes and the notice of dissolution for the Chapter.
The second series, Correspondence, covers the period from 1967 to 1978. This series includes a collection of the correspondence between the Northern Virginia Chapter and its members, arranged alphabetically. This series also includes photographs and drawings from the Chapters members, as well as maps and newspaper clippings. These documents record the findings and investigations of the Chapters' members and provide information about the history of the region.
The third series, Subject Files, covers the time between 1967 and 1978. This series includes information about the Northern Virginia Chapters' bylaws, invoices, and charter members. Also included in this collection is information about the Chapters' annual meetings and the American Association for State and Local History Award. This series chronicles the history of the Northern Virginia Chapter and its activities in the 1960s and 1970s.
The fourth series, Printed Material, ranges from 1964 to 1980. The series contains the publications of the Northern Virginia Chapter and includes the Chapter newsletters and brochures. Additionally, the series includes the publications "Echoes of History" and "Headquarters Heliogram," which contain articles from the Chapters' members and detail their findings and history of the region.
The fifth series contains oversized items from the 1970s, including unidentified newsletters and other publications from the Northern Virginia Chapter.
Arrangement
Organized into five series:
Series 1: Northern Virginia Chapter Business, 1969-1979 (Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1967-1978 (Boxes 2-9)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1967-1978 (Boxes 9-10)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1964-1980 (Boxes 11-12)
Series 5: Oversize, 1970s (Box 13)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other collections of organizations and personal papers that document planning in Northern Virginia. Many of these collection are related to the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Douglas, Henry H.
Corporate Names:
Pioneer America Society.
Subjects:
Historic Preservation--Virginia.
Contents List
- Series 1: Northern Virginia Chapter Business 1969-1979, (1 box)
  The first series, Northern Virginia Chapter Business, covers the period of 1969 to 1979. This series includes the Chapter history, membership, newspaper clippings, progress sheets, and a notice of dissolution.
  - Calendar, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interest Sheets, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Members and Membership, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notice of Dissolution, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Progress Sheets, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Correspondence 1967-1978, (7.5 boxes)
  The second series is a collection of correspondence between the Chapter and its members from 1967 to 1978. The series is organized alphabetically and contains letters, newspaper clippings, photographs, maps, and drawings.
  - Bagdon, Vincent J., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bartlett, Fred, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bernstein, Joel, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bloom, John Potter, 1972, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Photograph "The office of the Tombstone Prospector, a newspaper started in 1887."
  - Boss, Edward, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brabner-Smith, John, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brandt, Lawrence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Photographs (9) "The Rockbridge Mill, Missouri", "The Hodgson Mill, Missouri"
  - Briggs, Ferol, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Photographs (17) "Tomahawk Mill, Bedford County, Virginia", "Muddy Creek Mill, Tamworth, Cumberland County, Virginia", "Solitude Mill, Fluvanna County, Virginia", "Woodson's Mill, Nelson County, Virginia", "Spicer's Mill, Orange County, Virginia", "Aldie Mill, Loudoun County, Virginia", "The Burwell-Morgan Mill, Clarke County, Virginia", "The Tide Mill at Poplar Grove, Mathews County, Virginia", "Trenton Mills, Cumberland County, Virginia", "Cow Creek Mill, Gloucester County, Virginia", "Byrd Mill, Louisa County, Virginia", "Merrie Mill, Albemarle County, Virginia", "Walker Mill, Albemarle County, Virginia", "Jefferson Mill, Albemarle County, Virginia", "Graves' Mill, Madison County, Virginia", "Repton Mill, Madison County, Virginia"
  - Briggs, Lee, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Photographs (4) "Order for Morning Prayer, The Book of Common Prayer, 1754 Folio Edition", "Harold J. Spelman"
  - Bucher, Robert, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Burton, Tommye S., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Photographs (2) "The McCormack House, Prince William/Haymarket, Virginia"
  - Butler, Benjamin and Natalie, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bye, Ranulph, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Byrd, R.L., 1973, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cabell, Earle, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Candee, Richard, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Capron, John D., 1968-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Carner, Clara Hill, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cartwell, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cavender, Anthony P., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Childs, Patricia; (Moore's Store), 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chitwood, W.R., 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clements, William M., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Conner, E.R., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Conner, Prairie, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Couture, Richard; "James River Canal," 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cozzens, Arthur B., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Photographs (3) "Carl Hamman, gunsmith, Steelville, Missouri"
  - Dawson, Roger R., 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Photographs (9) "Colonial Antiques advertisement", "Old Leesburg-Alexandria Turnpike"
  - Day, Craig, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Deeley, Mary Jane, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Sketches (3) "Truro Church, Fairfax, Virginia", "Fairfax Court House, Fairfax, Virginia", "St. Mary's Church, Fairfax Station, Virginia"
  - Denmen, Clayton C., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Dickey, John M., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Doerken, Bill, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Echoes," 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Elvin, Jane, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Photographs (7) "The Fairfax Herald"
  - Emerson, Charles, 1968-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Postcards (8) "Greetings from San Francisco, California", Photographs (2) "Charles Emerson"
  - Friis, Herman, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Games, Marshall, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gamble, Bob, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Contact Sheet "Aldie, Virginia. Houses"
  - Givens, David, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Glassie, Henry, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Godfrey, Arthur, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Goodwyn, Frank, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gott, John K., 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Photographs (3) "E.S. Renalds and Company's Store, Marshall, Virginia", "H.L. Groome, Station Agent, Marshall, Virginia", "Southern Railroad Depot, Marshall, Virginia" Maps (2) "Fauquier County, Virginia"
  - Greguras, Fred, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Negatives (45) "Varina, Virginia", "Mt. Vernon, Virginia", "St. John's Episcopal Church, Richmond, Virginia", Virginia State Capitol, Richmond, Virginia", "Rockledge, Occoquan, Virginia", "Stagecoach Inn, Dumphries, Virginia" Photograph "Varina, Virginia"
  - Griffith, James S., 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Gritzner, Charles F., 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Grotewold, Andreas, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Gumb, Dana, 1971, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gunter, Charles, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hahn, Tom, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Photographs (19) "Rappahannock River Survey"
  - Hart, John Fraser, 1971, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Harwood, Herbert, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hatch, Winslow, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Heller, Homer, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hirst, Omer, 1970, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hodge, Robert, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hoyt, William, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Photographs (4) "Dogtown Common"
  - Hulan, Dick, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Map "Kentucky"
  - Hutton, Mary K., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Innes, Frank C., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Jeffers, Jack, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Photographs (2) "Old Blue Ridge Corn Crib", "Amish Man From the Blue Ridge"
  - Jones, Robert S., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Jordan, Terry, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Kauffman, Henry J., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Kegley, George, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kibbee, Lew, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Kiessling, Alice, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Kniffen, Fred, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Krause, Frank, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Photographs (6) "Murtaugh House, Manassas, Virginia", "Old Sudley Road", "Sudley Spring, Virginia", "Sudley Mansion, Fairfax, Virginia", "Sudley Sulphur Spring House, Manassas, Virginia"
  - Kury, Theodore, 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Labert, Darwin, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Lay, Edward, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Leigh, Hassell, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Leitch, Martha, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lewis, John, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lewis Pierce, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lewis, Vicki, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - MacCord, Lewis, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Markwood, Louis, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Marshall, Howard W., 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - McAtee, Robert, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - McKenna, Patrick, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - McTernan, Doug, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Photographs (6) "Farm, Fincastle, Virginia" Map "Fincastle, Virginia"
  - Millan, Lewis, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Milspaw, Yvonne, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Montell, Lynwood, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Moore, John H., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Photographs (2) "Fitzhugh Plantation House, Valleybrook, Virginia"
  - Morton, W. Brown III, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - National Geographic Magazine, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Netherton, Ross, 1969, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Nett, Charles, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Photographs (2) "Native Americans, Souix Tribe", Sketch "Log Cabin"
  - Newton, Milton, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Noble, Allen, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Nolan, Mary Lee, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Norman, Jane, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Odiseos, Phyllis, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Painter, Fred, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Peake Family, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Pennington, Robert, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Pennino, Martha, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Perdue, Charles, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Rafferty, Milton, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Richards, Tom, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Richardson, Herb, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Roberts, Warren, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Rogers, Lane, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Rose, Thomas, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Rosenberger, Francis, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Scheel, Gene, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Schwartz, Stuart, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Seme, Joe, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Drawings (6) "Winter at the Mill", Photograph "The Chapman-Beverly Mill, Virginia", Negative "The Chapman-Beverly Mill, Virginia"
  - Smith, Larry, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Sprouse, Edith, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Stansfield, Charles, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Steadman, Melvin, 1968-1974 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Stuntz, Mayo, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Taylor, R. Stephen, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Thompson, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Photographs (6) "Reverend Lawson Turner Thompson", "Garage and Dairy, Fairfax, Virginia", "Halman School, Fairfax, Virginia", "Grave Markers, Fairfax, Virginia", Negative "Halman School, Fairfax, Virginia"
  - Tilp, Frederick, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Map "Charles County, Maryland"
  - Tishler, William, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Trout, William, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Photographs (2) "The Work on the Rappahannock Canal", "Rappahannock Navigation, Lock 7", Maps (2) "Rappahannock Navigation"
  - University of Virginia, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Utley, Robert, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Viorst, Milton, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Vogt, Peter, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Photograph "Artistic Lighting Effect"
  - Wacker, Peter, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Walls, Aileen, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Walsh, Anthony, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Watkins, Malcolm, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Photographs (4) "Silverware", "China Plate", "Flask", "Marlboro Town Excavations"
  - White, Elizabeth, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Wiley, John, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Negative "1908 Cadillac"
  - Wilfong, James, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Wilhelm, Gene, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Wilhelm, Hubert, 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Wilkinson, Joyce, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Photograph "After A Raid on the Orange and Alexandria Railroad"
  - Williams, Ames, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Maps (2) "Four Mile Run Railroad Map", "District of Columbia", Photographs (6)"Provost Marshall's Office, Alexandria, Virginia", "Sketch of the 71st NY in Alexandria", "Sketch of Alexandria Episcopal Seminary", "Alexandria Oath of Allegiance", "Sketch of Sutler's Cart, Manassas, Virginia"
  - Williams, Lyle, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Wills, Mary Alice, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Photographs (2)"Possum-Nose Confederate River Battery", "Map of the Potomac", Map "Map of the Potomac River"
  - Wilson, Eugene, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Wrenn, Tony P., 1970-1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Wright, Russell, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Wyrick, Charles L., 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Yeager, Randolph, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Zelinksi, Wilbur, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series 3: Subject Files 1967-1978, (1.5 boxes)
  The third series contains subject files from 1967 to 1978. This series includes information on the Chapter's annual meetings, bylaws, charter members, invoices, survey sheets, and the American Association for State and Local History Award.
  - American Association for State and Local History Award, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Annual Meetings, 1969-1975 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Annual Meeting, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Barrett, William - Invoice, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Bylaws, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Charter Members, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Compliments, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Coordinates, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Council on Abandoned Military Posts, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Echoes" - complimentary copies, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Finances, 1973-1976 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Invoices - "Echoes," 1971-1974 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Invoices - envelopes, letterheads, 1967-1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Invoices - newsletters, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Japan Foundation Fellowship, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Logo Letterheads, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Members, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Obituaries, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Old Stone House, Washington D.C., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Programs, 1971-1972, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Publicity, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "Rails to the Blueridge" 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Survey Sheets, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - "West Virginia Hillbilly" Receipt, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Series 4: Printed Material 1964-1980, (2 boxes)
  The fourth series contains printed materials from the Northern Virginia Chapter. This series includes newsletters, the Chapter's "Echoes of History" and "Headquarters Heliogram" publications, and rough and final drafts of brochures.
  - Brochures - Final Drafts, 1970, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Brochures - Rough Drafts, 1967-1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Caves of Virginia" (Douglas, Henry, H.), 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Echoes of History," 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Echoes of History," 1969 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Echoes of History," 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Echoes of History," 1972 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Echoes of History," 1973 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Echoes of History," 1974 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Echoes of History," 1975 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - "Echoes of History," 1976 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Flyers, 1972, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Great American Hike" (Garvey, Ed), 1974 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Headquarters Heliogram," 1972, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Headquarters Heliogram," 1974 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Headquarters Heliogram," 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Headquarters Heliogram," 1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Headquarters Heliogram," 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1967, 1970, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Periodical," 1970, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Periodical," 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Periodical," 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series 5: Oversize 1970s, (1 box)
  Unidentified newsletters and other publications with proofs and negatives on page layouts.
  - Printed Material Page Proofs, 1970s (Oversize 13)